Guide to the Alyce Batchelder Collection of George Grebenstchikoff
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Alyce Batchelder Collection of George Grebenstchikoff
1898-1995
1947-1967
GEN MSS 589
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.69
(7 boxes)
The papers in this collection document the work of Alyce Batchelder as well as the correspondence and writings of George Grebenstchikoff (in Russian, Georgii Grebenshchikov). Alyce Batchelder's correspondence documents her work as literary executor for the George Grebenstchikoff estate after Grebenschikoff's death. George Grebenstchikoff's papers include professional correspondence and a collection of Russian medals. Correspondents include Dmitri Alexandrow, Pearl S. Buck (letters related to the Russian writer Ivan Bunin), Marjorie Kinnan Rawlings, George Sabo, Igor Sikorsky and Maurice J. and Lilli Swetland. The collection also contains a few early letters to George Grebenstchikoff's wife Tatiana that date from the years before her emigration to the United States. Realia in the collection include Russian military and religious medals.
Batchelder, Alyce
Grebenshchikov, Georgīĭ, 1882-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alyce Batchelder, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The University of Minnesota Immigration History Research Center has a significant collection of the papers of George and Tatiana Grebenstchikoff.
George Grebenstchikoff, 1882-1964
George Grebenstchikoff (in Russian Georgii Dmitrievich Grebenshchikov) was born May 6 (April 24 Old Style) 1883 in the Tomsk Oblast of Russia. In 1917 he married Tatiana Denisovna Stadnik, whom he met when she acted in a play he wrote. He published segments of his serialized novel Churaevy before emigrating to Paris (1920) and then the United States (1924). In 1925 he and Ilia Tolstoi founded the Churaevka artists' colony in Southbury, Connecticut, where Grebenstchikoff also directed the Alatas publishing house. The Grebenstchikoffs later moved to Florida, where George Grebenstchikoff taught creative writing and Russian literature at Florida Southern College from 1941 to 1952.
In addition to Churaevy, Grebenstchikoff's principal writings include the novel The Turbulent Giant (1940) and Egorkina zhizn' (published posthumously in 1966), an autobiographical work.
Alyce Batchelder befriended George and Tatiana Grebenstchikoff in Lakeland, Florida and became the literary executor for the George Grebenstchikoff estate in 1965.
Scope and Contents
The papers in this collection document the work of Alyce Batchelder as well as the correspondence and writings of George Grebenstchikoff. Alyce Batchelder's correspondence documents her work as literary executor for the George Grebenstchikoff estate after Grebenschikoff's death. George Grebenstchikoff's papers document a variety of personal and professional domains, including his activity to honor the Russian writer Ivan Bunin and his account of a lawsuit brought against him by Harold Hecht. The collection also contains a few early letters to George Grebenstchikoff's wife Tatiana that date from the years before her emigration to the United States.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four Series: Correspondence, Writings, Other Papers, and Personal Effects.
Authors, Russian -- 20th Century; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Medals -- Russia; Photographs; Alexandrow, Dmitri; Batchelder, Alyce; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973; Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1870-1953; Grebenshchikov, Georgīĭ, 1882-1964; Grebenstchikoff, Tatiana; Rawlings, Marjorie Kinnan, 1896-1953; Sabo, George; Sikorsky, Igor Ivan, 1889-1972; Swetland, Lilli; Swetland, Maurice J.
- Correspondence, 1913-1970; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Alyce Batchelder, George Grebenstchikoff and Tatiana Grebenstchikoff. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically. General Correspondence A-Z is filed at the end of the George Grebenstchikoff subseries.
  Scope and Contents
  Alyce Batchelder's correspondence documents her activities as literary executor for George Grebenstchikoff's estate and includes several folders of letters to and from members of the Grebenstchikoff family in Russia.
  George Grebenstchikoff's correspondence is both personal and professional, addressing literary and religious topics as well as some of his legal troubles. Of particular interest are letters to and from Pearl Buck, chiefly relating to the writer Ivan Bunin.
  Tatiana Grebenstchikoff's early correspondence documents her relationship with her first husband and his family in the years before she married Grebenstchikoff and emigrated.
  - Alyce Batchelder
    - Alexandrow, Dmitri, 1964-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes a printed version of "Delo odinokoe"
    - Buck, Pearl S., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grebenshchikov, Ilia Nilolaevich, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Grebenshchikov, Ivan Dmitrievich, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Sabo, George, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes a letter from Ivan D. Grebenshchikov to George Sabo
    - Sikorsky, Igor I., 1964-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      Includes one newspaper clipping about Sikorsky and a pamphlet entitled "Sikorsky Amphibion S-38, 1930 Model"
    - Yarmolinsky, Avrahm, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - George Grebenstchikoff
    - Alexandrow, Dmitri, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Buck, Pearl S. and Richard J. Walsh, incoming and outgoing, 1950-1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
    - Debalta, Stephen L., incoming and outgoing, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hecht, Harold and Lillian, 1951, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes two photographs of Harold Hecht and George Grebenstchikoff and a typescript relating Grebenstchikoff's account of the lawsuit Harold Hecht brought against him
    - Leontii, Metropolitan of all America and Canada, 1954 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Rawlins, Marjorie Kinnan, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Rognedov, Alexandre, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Sedych, Andrei, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Swetland, Maurice Jack and Lili, 1916-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 20-23)
      Includes photographs and typescripts of poems and a memoir
    - Tenney, George L., 1942-1950 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Varnava, Patriarch of Serbia, 1936 January 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Wasson, Lacy Bell, 1944-1964 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Greeting cards, 1932-1956 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - General correspondence A-Z, 1924-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
      Includes unidentified correpondence, two photographs of Umov and several photographs of a painting by Miguel Hrisogono
  - Tatiana Grebenstchikoff
    - Batchelder, Alyce, 1962 June 26 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Grebenstchikoff, George, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Letters from Tatiana Grebenstchikoff's first husband Sasha and other members of his family, 1913-1917 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Includes an excerpt of Sasha's diary
- Writings, 1953-1967, undated; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series II is arranged chronologically.
  Writings consists of four folders of notes, typescripts and printed versions of Grebenstchikoff's writings.
  - Notes, holograph, 1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Sobratu," typescript, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Russian song," proof, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Poems in English, printed versions and typescripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Other Papers, 1924-1995, undated; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series III is arranged roughly chronologically.
  Other Papers includes photographs, prints, drawings, personal papers and clippings, chiefly relating to Russian-American emigre culture, Grebenstchikoff's death, and legal affairs.
  - Ephemera from the S.S. Leviathan, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Five pen and ink sketches of landscapes with trees, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Photographs, 1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Snapshots and portraits of George and Tania Grebenstchikoff, Dmitri Alexandrow and others
  - Papers related to Olga, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1948-1957, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Includes: photographs, newspaper clippings and an invitation
  - Legal and financial papers, 1964-1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 41-43)
    Includes: power of attorney, social security documents, checks signed by Alyce Batcheldor
  - Drawings for Grebenstchikoff memorial, [1964]
  - Obituaries and memorial, 1964, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Printed cards, landscapes and portraits, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Two painted cards of Russian musicians, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Six handcolored lithographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Ephemera from the Churaevka Tea House, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Clippings, 1951-1995 (Box 4, Folder 49-53)
  - Empty envelopes and folders, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Personal Effects, 1898-1955, undated; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series IV is arranged chronologically.
  This series contains some of Grebenstchikoff's personal effects, including memorial medallions, religious medals, a silver cigarette case, an oil lamp and a woven wall hanging.
  - Russian and German coins in a small box, 1898-1948 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Religious medal of Platon, Archbishop of North America, [1914?] (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Silver cigarette case, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Religious medal celebrating 950 years of Christian Russia, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - St. Petersburg medallion, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Defense of Sebastopol medallion, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Nicholas Roerich medallion, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Eight Christian crosses and a St. Anthony's medal, tied on a string, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Watch fob, undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Oil lamp, undated (Box art)
  - Hand woven and embroidered wall hanging, undated; 9 feet by 3 feet
  - Green felt strap with metal and glass beads, undated
- Oversize, 3.01; (2 boxes)
  - Drawings for Grebenstchikoff memorial (series III), undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Hand woven and embroidered wall hanging (Series IV), undated (Box 7)
  - Green felt strap with metal and glass beads (Series IV), undated (Box 7)